<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Patrick Trent Greiner</title>
    <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://patricktrentgreiner.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Patrick Trent Greiner</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© PTG - 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/media/pic.png</url>
      <title>Patrick Trent Greiner</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colonization, Slavery, and Path Dependencies in the Fossil Economy</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/project/historical_inequality/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/project/historical_inequality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The making of our modern world rested upon an expansive reorganization of peoples across the globe, as well as the socio-ecological relations that characterized their societies. One of the primary tools used to carry out this reorganization was racialization. The social construction of race facilitated and justified the enslavement of millions of people whose expropriated labor provided the fiber and energy that acted as the foundation of the industrial revolution. At the same time, colonial and settler-colonial processes provided access to resources and markets that were necessary to the ceaseless growth of industrial activity and warfare. These processes played a fundamental role in shaping the infrastructures, built environments, economies, political regimes, trade networks social constructions of race, distribution of resources, and distribution of power that modernity is built upon. In this project my co-author &lt;a href=&#34;https://patricktrentgreiner.com/author/julius-alexander-mcgee/&#34;&gt;Julius Alexander McGee&lt;/a&gt; and I explore the ways in which the histories of slavery and colonization are bound to the seemingly unstoppable inertia of the fossil economy. We use quantitative and historical methods to explore how the processes of colonization, settler colonization, and enslavement set nations on different development pathways in an increasingly globalized economic system. Making a globalized system of production, consumption, and disposal sustainable without also addressing the network of relations that was intentionally built upon racialized logics in order to facilitate mercilessly efficient systems of economic development predicted on the pursuit of growth for growth’s sake may not be possible, and is far from just. This project points to the need for direct intervention in historically entrenched forms of inequality, as well as where such interventions might best be aimed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inequality, Decoupling, and Sustainable Development</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/project/decoupling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/project/decoupling/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As the intensity of environmental change driven by the development of Humanity’s social and economic systems deepens, finding a way to reduce such change becomes ever more urgent. However, it is well acknowledged that the growth-oriented development of systems (i.e. cultural, economic, political) that structure our social relations is ineluctably tied to activities that rely on the extraction of natural resources and exploitation of sinks for the byproducts of our dominant mode of social organization. Identifying the social, political, and economic features of the social world that can move Humanity toward the widely held goals of universal improvements in human well-being and maintenance of earth systems that can support these improvements long into the future is critcally important. In this project, I, and many of my co-authors (&lt;a href=&#34;https://patricktrentgreiner.com/author/julius-alexander-mcgee/&#34;&gt;Julius Alexander McGee&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://patricktrentgreiner.com/author/christina-ergas/&#34;&gt;Christina Ergas&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://patricktrentgreiner.com/author/matthew-thomas-clement/&#34;&gt;Matthew Thomas Clement&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://patricktrentgreiner.com/author/jordan-fox-besek/&#34;&gt;Jordan Fox Besek&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://patricktrentgreiner.com/author/daniel-shtob/&#34;&gt;Dan Shtob&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://patricktrentgreiner.com/author/mackenzie-christensen/&#34;&gt;MacKenzie Christensen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://patricktrentgreiner.com/author/nathan-pino/&#34;&gt;Nathan Pino&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://patricktrentgreiner.com/author/carl-appleton/&#34;&gt;Carl Appleton&lt;/a&gt;) use a number of quantitative and historical methods to explore the ways that some improvements in human well-being (e.g. movement toward gender, economic, and racial inequality) re-structure development processes such that they are “decoupled” from environmental change. Put differently, I ask what social changes yield a society that is more equitable, sustainable, resilient, and robust.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Locked into Emissions- How Mass Incarceration Contributes to Climate Change</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/prisons/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/prisons/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>W.E.B. Du Bois and interdisciplinarity- A comprehensive picture of the scholar’s approach to natural science</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/dubois_science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/dubois_science/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Racial Justice is Climate Justice- Racial capitalism and the fossil economy</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/tapestry/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/tapestry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Long Can Neoliberalism Withstand Climate Crisis?</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/neoliberal_electric/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/neoliberal_electric/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are the Goals of Sustainability Interconnected? A Sociological Analysis of the Three E’s of Sustainable Development Using Cross-Lagged Models with Reciprocal Effects</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/recip_sdgs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/recip_sdgs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community water system privatization and the water access crisis</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/water_private/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/water_private/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gender inequality, reproductive justice, and decoupling economic growth and emissions- a panel analysis of the moderating association of gender equality on the relationship between economic growth and CO2 emissions.</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/gender_emissions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/gender_emissions/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Urbanization Good for the Climate? A Cross-County Analysis of Impervious Surface, Affluence, and the Carbon Intensity of Well-Being</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/urban_ciwb/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/urban_ciwb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The asymmetry of economic growth and the carbon intensity of well-being</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/asym_ciwb/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/asym_ciwb/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Renewable energy injustice- The socio-environmental implications of renewable energy consumption</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/renew_injustice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/renew_injustice/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing spatiotemporal multifunctional landscapes to support dynamic wildlife conservation</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/agbirds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/agbirds/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time, Power and Environmental Impact- A Growth Curve Model of the Relationship Between Temporal Change and CO2 Emissions Per Capita.</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/time/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/time/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can Reducing Income Inequality Decouple Economic Growth from CO2 Emissions?</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/income_inequality/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/income_inequality/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snakes in The Greenhouse- Does increased natural gas use reduce carbon dioxide emissions from coal consumption?</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/nat_gas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/nat_gas/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Divergent Pathways on the Road to Sustainability- A Multilevel Model of the Effects of Geopolitical Power on the Relationship between Economic Growth and Environmental Quality</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/divergent_paths/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/divergent_paths/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do slums change the relationship between urbanization and the carbon intensity of well-being?</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/slums/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/slums/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social drivers of water utility privatization in the United States- an examination of the presence of variegated neoliberal strategies in the water utility sector</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/water_neoliberal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/water_neoliberal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Environmental Consequences of Rural and Urban Population Change- An Exploratory Spatial Panel Study of Forest Cover in the Southern United States, 2001–2006</title>
      <link>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/rural_forest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://patricktrentgreiner.com/publication/rural_forest/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
